本视频由Blinkist赞助
This video is supported by Blinkist.
Challenging Minisatellite Payload, CHAMP: 挑战性小卫星有效载荷
2000年 德国一颗名为CHAMP的卫星发射入轨 用于研究地球大气
In the year 2000, a German satellite called CHAMP was launched into orbit to study the Earth's atmosphere.
当它飞过北极上空时
As it flew over the North Pole,
卫星遇到了一个密集的气团 让卫星开始减速
it came across a dense pocket of air which started to slow the satellite down.
尽管这个高度大气含量微不足道
Although the atmosphere is almost non-existent at this altitude,
但仍有极少量的大气悬浮在四周
there are still small traces of atmosphere floating around.
但在CHAMP穿越这块气团的时候
But when CHAMP passed through the pocket of air,
它探测到的空气密度竟然比预期值增加了两倍
it measured an increase in air density of almost double the expected value.
科学家们当时并没有意识到此事
Scientists weren't aware at the time,
但事实上该气团是由极光造成的
but this pocket of dense air was being caused by an aurora.
这些绚烂的光影在几个世纪以来一直吸引着人类
These dazzling displays of light have fascinated the human race for centuries.
人们花了几百年才揭开极光的秘密
Unlocking the mystery of auroras took hundreds of years -
而且科学家们至今还在不断学习
and today, scientists are still learning more.
在北极苔原深处 研究人员正在研究一种不同的极光
Deep in the Arctic tundra, researchers are studying a different kind of aurora
这种极光正不断导致我们的大气往外太空泄漏
which is causing our atmosphere to leak into space.
关于极光的记录可以追溯到史前壁画
Records of auroras date back to prehistoric paintings -
但第一次科学观测是在1790年由科学家亨利·卡文迪许进行的
but the first scientific observation was made in 1790 by scientist Henry Cavendish.
他使用三角测量法估计极光发生在地球表面上空100公里左右的地方
He used triangulation to estimate that auroras
were taking place around 100 kilometers above the Earth's surface.
随着时间的推移 科学家们了解到极光是太阳与地球相互作用的结果
Over time, scientists learned that auroras are an effect of how the Sun interacts with Earth.
地球有一个磁场 保护我们免受太阳风的影响
Earth has a magnetic field which protects us from the Sun's solar wind.
这些太阳风是由带电粒子组成的
These solar winds are made up of charged particles
它们从太阳射出 具有巨大的能量
which shoot out from the sun with enormous amounts of energy.
当带电粒子到达地球时 大部分都被我们的磁场挡住了
When the charged particles arrive at Earth, most of them are deflected by our magnetic field.
但在南北两极 它们可以偷偷穿过并与我们的大气层发生短暂的相互作用
But at the North and South poles, they can sneak through and briefly interact with our atmosphere.
当这些带电粒子碰撞时 它们的能量会转移到我们大气层的粒子中
These charged particles transfer their energy into the particles of our atmosphere when they collide.
这种相互作用会以光的形式释放出能量
This interaction releases energy in the form of light,
于是我们就能看到美丽的极光了
creating the beautiful display we know as the aurora.
氧气：黄色/红色
氮气：蓝色
粒子根据其类型和传递的能量 会释放出的特定颜色的光
Specific colors of light are released
depending on the type of particle and the amount of energy being transferred.
尽管极光所涉及的能量巨大
Despite the enormous amounts of energy involved in auroras,
但粒子很快就会恢复到正常状态 我们的大气层也不会受到伤害
the particles quickly return to a normal state and our atmosphere is unharmed.
有一段时间 科学家们认为氧气分子太重了 无法逃离地球引力
For a while, scientists believed that oxygen was too heavy to escape Earth's gravity -
所以当CHAMP在异常高海拔的太空探测到空气团的时候
so when CHAMP discovered pockets of air at unusually high altitudes,
他们也不担心氧气会离开地球
they weren't worried about it leaving Earth.
但当科学家开始研究太空中的近地区域时
But when scientists started to study the near Earth regions of space,
他们却发现大量的电离氧 而这只能来自地球
they found large amounts of ionized oxygen which could only have originated from Earth.
出于某种原因 我们大气层中的氧粒子获得了足够的能量 摆脱了地球的引力
Somehow, the oxygen particles in our atmosphere were getting enough energy to escape Earth's gravitational pull.
南北两极是磁场与地球接触的唯一点
The north and south poles are the only points where our magnetic field comes into contact with Earth.
磁场线与地球大部分表面平行 但向每一极弯曲
The magnetic field lines run parallel with most of the Earth's surface but curve towards each pole.
当太阳的带电粒子到达地球时
When the Sun's charged particles arrive at Earth,
它们会被迫沿着磁场线运动
they are forced to travel along the magnetic field lines,
导致大部分带电粒子在两极相遇 与地球大气层相互作用
causing most of them to meet at the poles where they interact with Earth's atmosphere.
在这一点上 带电粒子可以直接接触到我们的大气层
At this point, the charged particles have a direct path through to our atmosphere.
磁场中的这个空隙会产生一种被称为“尖端极光”的现象
This gap in our magnetic field creates a phenomenon known as the 'cusp aurora'.
借助这一现象 太阳风会在缝隙中被加速
With cusp auroras, solar winds are accelerated through the gap,
形成一个具有强烈热能和动能的区域
creating a very concentrated area with intense heat and kinetic energy.
当带电粒子与我们大气层中的粒子碰撞时
As the charged particles collide with the particles in our atmosphere,
它们会获得足够的能量摆脱地球引力 导致氧气泄漏到太空
they receive enough energy to escape Earth's gravitational pull, causing streams of oxygen to leak into space.
在北极几乎每天晚上都能观测到正常的极光
While a normal aurora can be observed almost every night in the Arctic,
而尖端极光只在北极在极夜时的正午时分发生
the cusp aurora only appears at midday when the arctic experiences a full day of darkness.
而尖端极光没有固定位置 不断在北极地区移动 导致它更加难以观测
To make it even more difficult to observe,
the cusp doesn't have a fixed position and it constantly moves around the Arctic regions.
但当这些绚丽的极光最终出现的时候
But when these colorful lights finally appear,
就意味着有数百吨的氧气正在逃离地球大气层
it signals that hundreds of tons of oxygen are escaping Earth's atmosphere.
虽然每天只能观察到很短的时间
Although this can only be observed for a short period of time each day,
但这只是实际发生的一小部分
this is only a fraction of what is actually happening.
当我们在紫外光波段观察地球时
When we look at the Earth in ultraviolet light,
我们可以发现极光是全天都在发生的
we can see that auroras are constantly happening throughout the day.
但地球并不是唯一一个经历极光的星球
But Earth is not the only planet to experience auroras.
哈勃太空望远镜通过在紫外波段观察木星
The Hubble Space Telescope was able to capture
发现木星上发生了非常类似的极光过程
a very similar aurora process happening on Jupiter by viewing it in ultraviolet light.
火星曾经和地球很像 但太阳风在数十亿年来剥蚀了它的大气层
Mars used to be a lot like Earth, but the solar wind stripped away its atmosphere over billions of years,
留下了遍布星球的小磁场
leaving small magnetic fields dotted around the planet.
最终 我们的大气也会经历类似的命运
Eventually, our atmosphere will experience a similar fate.
每天 超过100吨的大气会散逸到太空
Every day, over 100 tonnes of our atmosphere escapes into space.
幸运的是 以这个速率 我们的大气层需要数十亿年才能完全消失
Fortunately, at this rate, it would take billions of years for our atmosphere to completely disappear.
虽然极光是我们夜空中的众多奇观之一
And while auroras are one of the many wonders of our night sky,
但其背后的原理则是一个振聋发聩的警钟 提醒人类我们的星球是多么脆弱
the process behind them is a shocking reminder of how fragile our planet really is.
While doing research for this video,
the most fascinating bits of information were hidden away in various books and research papers.
It's 2020 and most of us don't have the time to fully dive into a book and absorb all of its information.
For those of us that want to learn more but don't have the time, Blinkist has you covered.
This app does an amazing job of condensing all the information in a book down to just 15 minutes for you to read or listen to!
If you want to try this out for free, sign up using the link below to get 7 days of unlimited access to over 3,000 non-fiction books.
Blinkist covers almost every topic imaginable but I'd recommend reading ‘A Brief History of Time' by Stephen Hawking.
After your free trial, you'll also get 25% off the normal membership price.
This special offer is only available for the first 100 people who sign up using the link below.
This is a great way to support the channel, so you can continue to learn more about all things space.
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.